So today we are still in our quarter 2, and we will discuss access
control, right? Um, OK,
so there are some product recording about the access control
models and especially for the set URD approach
used by operating system. OK, we all are using either Linux operating
system, Mac system, or the Windows operating system,
right? So we will discuss how those operating system is managing.
The users' um authorization to different
programs and files in the system, right?
So we will focus on that Linux operate system access control today.
But in my pre-elect recording, I've touched um how
those permission uh were, should be read,
right? Those, those numbers mean what, right?
So, uh, I probably will skip some detail because I have
kept them in my recording, pre-elect recording.
Um, but I'll still explain a little bit today in,
in our lecture. Um, but you can see probably another
case study, which is movie database system management.
Um, so how should we manage different type of user
and their access to the movie? Right? So in that
one, you can see the rule-based access control method
and the rule-based, sometimes we also call that
attribute-based access control, right? So rule-based or
rule-based, right? R U L E. Rule-based also
sometimes we just call that attribute attribute based ABAC,
RBAC, that will mean two different types of methods.
And in those models, we also have DEC and the MAC,
which is discretionary access control and the mandatory access control.
Right, so different model, access and control model.
So access control is always about give the right authorization to
different level of users, right? But of course,
in that process, we have different model we can refer to.
And when we design some database system.
Uh, similar to this movie database system design,
you should also think about how should you manage the
access control right to different level of users,
right? And how should they grant those access level,
right? And then another case study we focus on is
the operating system access control, right?
So what and how that access controls applied to the operating
system and what are the relevant security issues,
right? So that's all our objectives today.
Um, so a second control, um, In this
lecture, it is focused on operating system case study.
Um, so with the operating system, you probably understand
in, um, Operating system, we have the
subjects, right? Subjects may mean users or programs,
right, or some commands, um, which is, OK,
the users will use commands to, to call some programs to do tasks
for this user, right? So we call them subjects.
And these subjects have the diff, have different permission to
the objects. The objects can be The file pipes
and sockets, OK, in the system, right? So when we talk about the
permission, we normally talk about the read,
write, execute permission. To this object,
OK, from subject to the object, right? So in old time
with that um traditional Linux or Unix system.
It is using discretionary access control model,
which means, OK, random set access
control. If not, not random, I mean, if a user
wants to access something and he can always change his own permission to,
to do something with that object, right?
And so, well, yeah, depends on the, on the
request, right? So the There is a root user
can always do this change mode. OK, so C
HMOD means change mode, um to 777.
Why it's a 777? Um, 77 means in
primary, I'm sorry, in binary code, which is Or
1, right? So it's a 111 which is a
number 7, right? So if we have all 111,
so which is a full permission, right, to uh use them,
right. 777, which means we have read,
write, and X permission for owner himself,
and the middle three digits means for the group user um
themselves, and then they have a full permission.
And for other user, any other user can also read,
write, and execute. So which is a full permission,
um, access, right? So, but the route can always use a change
mode com command. To grant everyone access depending
on the request, right? So that's a traditional Unix.
Um, we call that discretionary access control model.
But with the security enhanced Linux, we have the mandatory
access control on top of discretionary access control because
people found, oh, if we grant, if the route always grant uh
777, which may cause a lot of issue, and we have to
have something um mandatory control, and we don't allow
those um permission to be granted in some very special cases,
right? We have those mandatory access control on top of the DAC which
is safer. And then it will grant
limited privilege to minimum, OK, to reduce this possible harm,
right? So that's a, that's uh some change from traditional to
security enhanced Linux uh nowadays, right?
And a good point to notice is the malware can always run at a
user um process, access control level. So which
means If we uh turn on our computer, we
run our computer as a normal user, and the malware when it
gets through the system, um, the malware can have the access
level as a normal user because we're logging into our system with a normal user.
And then in that system, uh, everything runs with a normal
user's access level, right? malware, if he,
if the malware runs by, um, in the system,
it also runs at normal user success level.
But if you always log into your computer uh system
in your superpower, powerful admin
user access level, which means admin
users' access level is higher than the normal user.
And you can always access your system file and some protective file,
right? You can run some programs which only executable by the
root user, by, by the admin user, right?
And then the malware, when, uh, malware,
OK, with admin, uh, access, malware can also
access to those protected files or programs,
right? So which means If you don't need to,
you really shouldn't always log into your system with um Academy user
type, user, right? You should just use your normal user's privilege
um to log into your system that gives a better protection to your system.
OK. OK. To talk about the access um
control, uh, in the system, OK, in any operating system,
we sometimes probably have to consider uh how to ground the proper level
of access to different objects, right?
And then let's just starting, uh, let's just start some um password
dilemma, which was um initially, like,
mm problem, initial problem. The system has to
solve, right? So the password is a file,
right? Password file stored in Linux operating system in this place I've
ever shown you, OK, in our, um, Linux operating system.
And you can see the permission for that shadow file,
which is in here, right? Um, it has this
permission. It has this permission. OK. You just read this permission
three digits by three digits, right? So very first three
digits is RW, which means that's the
permission for, uh, for owner himself. And
then here is the owner's uh user, right?
So which means this shadow file belongs to root user.
And that's the group ownership. So, um, the group
ownership is a shadow group, OK, group user.
So then these three permissions, the very first three
digits is the RW dash, which means the root
user has the read and write permission, but
there's no other like executable permission here,
right? And then if it's for the root, uh sorry,
group user, if you your user privilege belongs to a
shadow user, right, shadow group. And you can read OK,
if you have that group ID you can read but you can't write,
right? And then if you are other user, the last three digits means
the last uh other other user permission.
So if you Uh, other users such as our, um,
user privilege, our user ID is a lab user in our
cloud, um, Linux operating system, right?
So we are lab user, we are in this type,
and we are other user. And then as other user,
we don't have read permission, we don't have write permission,
we don't have other, uh, executable permission,
right? So those are all da da da da, the
very last digit, uh, 33 digits.
OK, so as other user, as a lab user, OK,
and then we have no permission at all to this shadow
file, right? And then, as other user,
if we want to change our own password, what
the system uh should do, right? Should do to this
request. So the system think, OK?
Maybe I shouldn't change a password for you.
In that case, um, of course,
It's, it's, if we don't allow any change,
uh, that's not reasonable, right? The system must allow a normal user to be able
to change his own password, right? Then we have to
grant the allow to this shadow file to, to grant,
grant, grant the right permission. There should be a right here,
right, in the middle, right? And there should be maybe a read
permission as well, right, but yeah. For the other user.
However, if we grant the right permission,
which also means other user passwords, you can also
change probably if we have the right permission here in the middle,
right, which means the normal user can also write to any field
of this shadow file. So, so the system doesn't want you to
do that, right? Of course. Then there shouldn't be a right permission,
right? So there shouldn't be a right permission in that case.
So, which is the system can face this, this,
this problem. And then, however, the system may grant you a
final level access control, fine-grained access
control, which means he allows you to change your own field,
but he doesn't want to, want you to change others um
password. However, if we go through this direction here,
right, which means Um, we want the
user can change his own password but no other password.
We have to have that uh file-level granularity or sometimes we call
that field-level granularity. If
the system has a way to do that, and the system has to have
Very complex access control for many different types of file,
right? So if we, we allow this happening,
which means access operating system's complexity will be hugely
increased, right? And then so for a system,
this is only a password changing task, right?
And we have this dilemma, the system. Doesn't,
OK, if we don't have the proper access control,
um, granted, and then we probably very hard to,
OK, to manage this, right? So whether we should grant the right,
no. Um, but we also don't want the com operating system complexity to be
very high, right? So that what to do with this
password changing task and this shadow file,
right? How should we change the permission here?
And it kind of the dilemma the system is facing when he designs
um the access control model for any operating system.
So here is what the system is doing, right?
So it is using this two-tier approach.
Two-tier approach, which means there are some programs,
OK, and there are some um protected resource,
right? So instead of allowing a user to touch this
protected resource directly, we have some.
Second layer here in the middle, so we call that two-tier.
And then which means the operating system will rely
on extension to enforce fine-grained access
control. Now we need that fine-grained access control,
but we don't want the operating system complexity to be increased by himself.
So we designed some other program which are the
privileged program. And to do the task
for the um user for normal user, so which
means OK the shadow file is now the protected resources right
resource and then the password this program,
OK, which is actually this set UID program,
OK, which, OK password is one set UID program.
The set UID program is this privileged program.
So he allows a user ID to be set
to be a route temporarily. They call that set UID,
the user ID. Approach. OK. Password
is this approach, OK, is one program in this set UID
approach. So this program, what this program is,
uh, is able to do is he can be used to change the
shadow for normal user, OK? And only right ball
to root a normal user right is restricted,
so you know that, right? So with the shadow and you can see only the root user
can have the right permission. But not other normal user,
right? However, for a normal user, we have to allow him to do
a changing, password changing, right? Then this normal user can,
instead of touching this protected resource by himself directly,
instead of doing that, he is calling a special privileged
program. Which is set UID program. Which
is this program password, OK, belongs to this URD program.
So, calling this program, and then,
When you call that program, OK, you can run that program with a special lifted
privilege of of root user. So, during your
call that program, your user ID has been set to a
different user ID which is a root user.
Although you are still a normal user, you're running with,
you're running this program with your normal user ID.
Right, so the real user ID when you run that program through
a real user ID, a lab user, right, a lab user.
However, The actual effective user ID will
become a root. So when you read this permission,
OK, you can read here, which now is
RWS. OK. RWS means
the your user ID has been set to a
root user, OK, to a root user. So
Um, It doesn't say here, but when
we, when we run this program in the lab user's
account, we run this one, and that last digit here
means you have turned on your special user ID which
is a root user, because this program um is a
root-owned program, so the ownership is a root.
So when you do S here, so S has been Um,
as represented here, a normal user can run with a
special owner privilege to run this program.
If this program belongs to a root user and then when you,
a normal user, lab user run this program,
you will be granted a privilege belonging to the owner
of this program, which is a root, OK, temporarily.
And then you can then change the pro uh the function of this
program is to change your password. OK. So when you change the
password, and then your privilege is a root user,
OK. And then when you have that root user's
privilege. Now you can see You have the
right permission to touch the shadow file,
right? So which is why after you run this program,
you change your own password and the shadow file will be changed,
OK, um, through this password, OK,
PASDWD program. So this is how you change your
password. Um, basically, you are not touching that shadow
file by yourself. You're not allowed to have to touch it by yourself,
but you can use another program, which leads to your own
privilege temporarily. And then during that That period
of your lifted privilege and then you can change your own
password, but you can't change anything else password and that
PAS WD, the function of himself is only allowing you to
change your password. Right, your own field and that everyone,
when, when another user run that one, that user will also be granted a
temporary root privilege so that he can change his own field for
his password. And so that's how the operating system,
Linux operators solve this issue, right?
So, um. Using that set your idea approach and to
call for another program so that you can do this simple task,
right, you can touch those protected resources.
So that's a two-tier approach and then, and then this is very,
very much like a Superman. When he has some
task, he either delegate that task to a
normal user. So he grant a superpower to a normal
user, right? And then that's what we do in that cellulD approach.
Or another choice for him is to always do everything by himself.
We call that diamond approach, right? So he has two choices.
One is to grant a superpower to a normal user.
In that way, he has to define what
superpower, um, with that superpower, what function you can do.
You, you have very restricted um Action,
OK, with that superpower, right, the UID approach is
used in this way. So we always can do this superpower and delegate it to a
normal user or temporarily, right? You can only do whatever defined with
that superpower. That's um. Sell your ID approach.
Or if a superman doesn't trust anyone else,
he do everything, he does everything by himself,
we call that demon approach, right? So, or sometimes we call
that service approach. So Windows operating system is actually using that service
approach, OK, so in Windows operating system you always see a lot of programs running in
the background, right? That's because of the system himself is doing.
All jobs by himself, right, but the Linux operating system actually
has um Used this set UID approach, which
allows a normal user to have the temporary
root privilege or the privilege of another user and then he can,
um, then the system is more effective, sorry,
efficient, efficient actually. That's why Linux is more efficient than
compared with Windows operating system, OK.
Um, so the set UID approach, um, this is one example we
have shown you with that password changing task.
And There are normally we call two user IDs.
When we have this set UID approach running,
right, what we mean here is when we, when the normal user,
lab user here is this, is running this program.
The real user ID is a lab user, but
the effective user ID becomes rode temporarily.
This can be readable or can be um recognized
by reading this permission here. When you see there's a S,
which means that cell U ID has been used here.
Right, so which allows a different effective
user ID, OK, from the real user ID to be,
to be used and then so that a normal user,
lab user can be temporarily granted that root user
effective ID, uh, yeah, with that root privilege,
OK, to do something. Which is only permit permittable
by that root user. OK, because the shadow file can only be changed by root
user, which is why we need that root user privilege to change the
shadow file. By running this program, a normal user is granted that root
user privilege temporarily, and then this,
this allows this normal user to change his own password,
which um was part of the shadow file, right.
So this is a different effective user. If we,
OK, I mean, in my pre-elect recording, if you check the effective user ID
actually you can see that one becomes the root user rather than the.
Real user ID anymore, right? So it, it will be a different user ID.
OK, when you have, when you see that, the,
when you see this permission like this, and which means this programs allows a
normal user to run this program with its ownership,
its owner's privilege, which is root here.
Right, OK. So that's a set UID
example. But when we read those um number,
right? Normally, uh, we can identify them by a
number or by reading those like these numbers,
right? Um, but why we call that, sorry, why we call that,
um, Set UID, which means
we actually set some single digit and to change the user ID.
So once that UID is used.
For example, that 7555. Um, here, um,
the example here which is the first three digits is a 7.
And this one is a 5, right, and this one is a 0,
right? So if we have a 5, which should be a 101,
right? 101, which is a 5 permission, OK.
And then the very 1st 4 means normally we have another
000 at the beginning. OK, so which is
0. So it's, it's a 0755, but when it's a
4755, which means 100, OK, so the very first
digit has become from 0 to 1. So which is why when
we have 100 we have a 4, we have 4 here,
right. So when you read that S appears, right,
as appears like this example here, we have this S,
then we know, oh, OK. The very first three digits
has become 100, so which is a 47 something
uh permission. So, when we use this set UID approach,
um, the original permission might be 0755,
but now becomes 4755, which means that for that
special program that permission can be granted to a normal user
and a set UID approach can be applied to that program
so that a normal user can run that program with a different effective user
ID, right? Because that RWS can also be seen
from listing those permissions, OK, which behind
that RWS which actually is these numbers here shown,
OK. And then of course sometimes you can also see set GID
set group user ID. OK, this means group user ID,
uh, which means a different, um, permission,
so which is a 2755, which means this one instead of being
100, which is 010, OK, very first three
digits becomes a 2, OK, 010, which is the second
digit here, OK. So, now if you read
something like this, which is actually uh
RWS in the middle three digits, right?
And this one means a group ownership. OK,
so, uh, which now it's, uh RWS, which means
the GID approach has been used, OK, and then where the
very first three digits becomes 010, OK.
So if you read what this means is this test,
OK, directory is a directory, right? So very first digit means it's either
a file, a directory, or a link or something else,
right? And then the permission, the real permission is read uh from this
RWX RWS R dash X, OK.
So that that bit has effect on both files and directory
um except GID bit so which means this, this one,
OKs here means this bit OK means the second
digit in those very first three triplet,
yeah, first three digits. That that GI set
GID bit has effect on both files and directory.
So this is a directory, so when, when that means.
Um This directory,
um, if it's a file, then it will be run with the privilege of the
group who owns the file, not with the user
who started it. So if it's a file, then when a normal
user like a lab user is running that one,
then the lab user is running with this group owner.
Privilege, right? So the group owner has the
Read and write um permission. And then,
so the, the normal user can have that group.
Group's privilege to to when when he runs
this program. But now here is a folder, right,
so it's a directory and then if it's a directory this one
enables the group of files created inside this directory
inherit. It's group ownership of the parent folder,
not the group of users who created them,
right? So it allows a normal user like, like lab user to create
a folder inside this test. But those folder would have the
uh group ownership of that parent folder,
which is this special group ownership, right?
Rather than um the owner becomes the users themselves,
right? So the group ownership would always be this one.
So that allows that to happen. Right, so because
thats means that that GID approach has been used and
then there is a special um digit which is 0 from
000 to 010 and the second digit has been,
has become 1. OK, so it's just using this uh single
digit control um to allow the system to know
what has happened and this S. Showing, OK,
this S digit is for the user who interact
with the shell with the operating system to recognize,
oh there has been something special arranged here where With
this digit means the operating system has arranged some special
permission behind thiss letter, right, which is
this permission here, right, which is that 010 has been
organized has been allocated to this special folder or
file right we have different meanings. And then again here
we sometimes see this sticky bit, right,
so which means it's 1755, then that means the very first
digit. From 000 becomes 001.
So if it's this, then that's a sticky bit turned on.
And what that means is OK, we give one example of this,
and that is a temporary folder. And now you can imagine you have access to
your Linux operating system and you can also work something under this temporary folder,
right? And then, however, the system would like everyone to
create something or to work under this temporary folder,
OK. You can create another folder, you can create some file and save them in the temporary
folder, um, but You wish
any files created in this folder only modifiable by their
owners, right? And you shouldn't, the system shouldn't allow another
user to modify or delete the folder you
have created under this temporary folder.
Only you yourself can modify or delete
something there, right. However, of course,
you wish the other user can read. They can read,
can enter, but you, they can't execute. Excute means
uh maybe create something more and then or remove right
or edit that, that one. So that
is OK, recognizable by a T, OK by a T.
Um, to human beings, but behind this T, which means that
digit, is this, right? The operating system can recognize that
special arrangement by reading those numbers,
but to human beings, and we can recognize that one by reading that
RWX becomes RWT. Which
means the operating system only wants the files or the
folder uh owner, OK, who created them to be able to
modify or delete the files, OK, but, um,
yeah, of another user you can't delete other users,
you can, but you can do whatever you want for your own,
uh, created a file or folders under this TMP folder.
So this is a folder. Special permission,
um, user here. So the operating system always have,
have to find a way, um, to give some
power to the users, but they also want to have the proper
control for that power, right, for that access control.
Right? So these are the very special occasions you might see uh
when you go to your um workshop and you
can run this one, OK. And you can see that different
arrangement, OK? And now you understand what's behind,
OK, are those numbers playing around and then the system would recognize different
number. And then no different arrangement has been granted to this special
folder or files or programs, right? So these are how the operating system
actually manage this access control, right.
And of course now let's see what may happen with this access
control. And this is a very um easy example for you to understand,
but, um, of course, in reality, that's also what happened,
OK? Um, and then. So, you can see in
principle, this set UID approach is secure and the system always runs a
different bit control and so that it recognize different permission,
right? So it, it allows the normal user can also escalate some
privilege when they need to, right, but they do not grant the
privilege to us that directly, and the user can only do whatever
included in the program. This is different from grant uh direct granting a
privilege like Sudu. P Suu is always just,
uh, yeah, give you super users, um. Power,
OK, to, to do something, right? And when you run that studio and
your real user ID and effective user ID will be changed to a different,
OK, super user. But when we run this set your ID approach,
we actually, our real user ID is to ourselves,
but our effective user ID will become um owner of
that program, right? So The superpower,
Superman, when they grant the superpower to a normal user,
they wish them. User, normal user can only do
restrictive behavior. Right, so this is similar to the Superman.
OK, they designed a special computer chips,
right, um, and attach that super, sorry,
attach that computer chips to their supersuit so that the user,
normal user wearing those supersuits can do something powerful but only
do something uh designed by that super um suit
chips, right. Which is the, the, the design program.
I think can only run those. So this is a simple example to show
you um if we have something um like designed
pro not properly and what could happen right the
Superman. Ask a user, normal user to, to do
some task to, to, to, to save this to hostage,
right? So which where the direction should be going north and
turn left, right, going north and turn left.
So what he has designed is to um grant some
superpower, giving that super suit and with the computer chips,
OK, program designed is flying north and turn left so that
This delegate, this normal user can save this hostage.
However, this, this delegate, this normal user,
he always wants to use that superpower to fly north and turn right to
the bank to, to steal something. Right.
Then Um Then he found some
flaw in the code and he can change the fly north and turn left,
but instead of facing up, Um, to the north,
so he flying backwards and turn left. So
he's flying north, but facing down and turn left.
He gets to the bank direction rather than facing up and to the north
and turn the left. So, um, so he has that superpower and to do something,
right? And then, and then of course, the Superman found this delegation
uh has something wrong, and then the code can be exploited.
So what he can do is he very um
carefully write his code. And indicate
Flying north and turn west rather than turn left,
right? So turn west. And then, so that,
um, then this delegate who has got that
superpower and super suit, right? So he still wants to break
into that bank with that power. So what he could do
is, he can still fly north and turn west,
but then The west is actually east. So what he,
he can do is he asks someone else of his friend,
right, his friend, Ask his friend to do some
electromagnetic controlling or changing some equipments
nearby, so make the compass on his supersuit doesn't work properly.
So that supersuit says, OK, west, but which is actually an
east. Right, so that code can still be
broken and then can still allow this evil person to
go, let go north and, and west, OK, which is actually
east. So go to the bank. So this is what may happen in
reality. So, um, there are some set UD approach used.
Um, but that people always find some flaw in the program design,
and then they change the design and then they do something evil with that
superpower, right? So this is actually what happened and now you can see something
probably with this fighting and defending um
if the access control is not properly designed or some superpower
is exploited by bad people, what could happen,
right? I'll give you two examples. One is the Um,
say the approach doesn't grant the right access control,
right? And then the second example would be the race condition,
um, vulnerability, which is, which shows you how the
code, um, exploitation may be, um, may, may
cause the problem, right? So this one, I'll probably go,
uh, need just another 5 minutes. And if you do have other session,
please, please feel free to go. I'll just keep everything in recording.
OK. So, um, this is a very old time,
maybe more than 10 years ago. The VI is editor,
right? Um, it's um Link to
this. Editor, which can work as a text text editor,
right, so you probably have used this one in your workshop and then that's the
permission it has, right? And now if we run this
one with that permission, what may happen here is this one,
OK, Apache.config, right, which is a web server
configuration file. It's permission is a root root and the mode
0644. So I'm writing this, root root means it
belongs to the root user and the group ownership is the root,
group, right? And then this permission is
000 and 6 is
110 and 4 is 100
and another 100, right? So that's 0.
644, right. So now what that
means is for a root user, he
can read, OK, read and write, right?
For a group user he can read. OK, I'll put dash here and
read. And for other user he can read right
so which means if you are other user, if you are lab user,
right, our normal user um privilege is just
lab user which is normal user and belongs to the other user type.
If we are a lab user, we can read the configuration file but we
can never write, so there's no write permission for our lab user,
right, so we can't write, OK, we can't execute as we can only
read, read. So now, um, but for the,
for the root user he can read and write,
right? For the root user he can read and write.
And now you can imagine when we use VI to open this configuration
file. Because VI is run by a lab user here,
right, but the VI's permission is RWS
as here. And behind the scene which reads
as 100. Right, and
111 uh
101 and 101, right. What this is what
behind. So it, it means a normal user can be
listed as a root user's privilege and can
We can, uh, yeah, you, you can have that root privilege temporary,
right? So that set UID approach has been allowed and used by this
VI, right, which means a normal user when you run that VI
you can temporarily have that. Root privilege because it belongs to root,
right? You can temporarily have that root privilege and to,
to open something and temporarily, when you open that
file, you have that root privilege temporarily.
And then with that root privilege, I mean at the time when you run
this program, your real user ID RUID
is a lab user, right, but your effective user
ID, EU ID is actually a root user,
right, but with the root user privilege you can do right,
you can do read and also write. Right, because you now,
you are, you are the root user, OK.
Your EU ID is the root because VI allows that,
VI allows that. OK, so then you are the root
user. You can read and write, which means for a neb user when he
runs that one and he actually was granted that root privilege temporarily
and he can write to this web service confusion file which is
not right, OK, so the system should not grant.
Uh VI to be this set UID program.
And then if that one happens in Ubuntu back
into that time, and then we test this issue.
OK. So, but of course nowadays you can go to your Linux
optimism. You can check what is the privilege or what is the
permission for VI, and you can check nano.
You can check P Picco as well. You can check all this editor whether
it has become uh more like
restricted permission, right, whether it has somes permission somewhere.
Um, if it has like what has been designed or given by Ubuntu
before and it has this problem issue, right,
so allows a normal user to access to this web server configuration file
and then. Uh, which shouldn't happen, OK.
And another example is this risk condition vulnerability.
What happens here is the system himself,
right, um. OK, when you have the balance,
bank balance $100 and you want to request to withdraw $90
and then after that one, and the balance should be calculated and you only have $10 left,
right. However, you had another request to withdraw $90.
And then you can imagine if your 2nd request of withdrawing
$90 arrives. Before the new balance
is calculated and saved. And then you are
able to withdraw 2 times $90 right? So
which is, um, the reason is because of
the checking balance timing is not
correct. Or your two requests arrives at the same time,
OK, uh, to withdraw $90. So that timing is very critical
here. So the system, if Yeah, the, I
mean, if a person happens to do something evil
before you drop down your privilege, and then that something evil,
OK, could happen, right, before the privilege was dropped.
So which is why when we say the CUID approach is supposed to be very safe and
if it's well maintained by the system, there will not be something bad happening,
right? However, there will always be some vulnerability existing in
the system, such as this risk condition vulnerability.
So when the timing of signal is important,
we call that two signals racing each other to influence the output.
We call that race condition. OK. When there's a race condition.
And then the bad people can always try to exploit that root
privilege before the privilege is dropped down,
right? So, this is actually happens in 2016 with the
system and it's a very famous exploitation.
It's called dirty cow. Dirty cow means dirty copy
on right. So it's actually exploiting this kind of race condition
vulnerability. To modify the protected files,
OK, which is supposed to be readable by other users because some
programs allow the other user to lift their own privilege.
And then um the, the malware or those dirty
cow exploit, they get exploit that
privilege before the privilege was dropped down,
OK? And then they can grant this dirty copy and right,
OK, to those protected file before the privilege was dropped down.
So that's what happened in the system if we Have that sell your
idea approach um applied to the system, um,
but when there are some vulnerability existed there,
um, a similar Situation could happen like
as those happen to those superpower granting,
uh, like superpower was granted to the normal user,
right, but it's not properly managed and then the code or the function of
the program was not well designed. And then something evil could happen,
right? So there's always this or that issue and this vulnerability or that
vulnerability and the people always find a way to exploit those vulnerabilities,
such as this, this dirty car, right? And then that cause issue.
So this is relevant to the access control,
right? So the system always have to find a way to define the right.
Permission level, right, like that VI and they identify the issue and they
actually solve the issue and then they change the permission not to be
as before, right, and they solve this, fix this issue,
but then there will always be other issues like this risk condition.
Um, and then the privilege should be dropped down maybe before
you activate on other things, but the system always has this
risk condition vulnerability, and then there,
there's something evil could happen. OK.
Um, of course, that's linked to access control.
And then maybe more um to consider to the system which is accountability,
and we would say, oh, is a AAA, right? The first A means
authentication, the second A means access control,
the third A means accountability. But the second aid doesn't
appear always to every system, right? Always,
yeah, not, not, not a must do task for all the systems.
Sometimes it's just not necessary. Um, but if we have that accountability,
of course, we could have all that event logger,
uh, for different types of equipment, right?
And when there are something bad happening,
And we can also identify what is happening and to what part through this event
logs. So that's about accountability, but we won't go to uh
details about accountability. Um, the main thing we were talking about is
authentication, access control that is included in every system.
That's a problem, um, which has to be faced by
or designed by all the system. OK. So that's all for this week.
Thanks for Your attention, um, maybe we'll see you in your
workshop, OK.